Hi, everyone.
Welcome back.
Okay, so last lecture.
We finished off our first project, and now in this lecture, we are going to be doing our second project.
And our second project is a loan analysis by a company called Blue Bank.
So I'm going to open the project brief and we can give it a read.
Okay, so this is the project brief, which will be available in your class lecture notes and we can
scroll down to project two.
All right, let's give it a read.
Blue Bank is a bank in USA that has a loan department which is currently understaffed.
They supply loans to individuals and don't have much reporting on how risky these borrowers are using
Python and Tableau.
I'd like to see a report of borrowers who may have issues paying back the loan, and those are the data
files.
So you should have downloaded the data files.
Remember to download them and save them into one folder for this whole course just so we can refer back
to it.
And then let's just go on to Python.
Okay.
So I've opened Spider and first things first.
So make sure that your value in underscore sales pie folder.
If you still have it open, make sure that it's saved so you can command or control.
Yes.
Or save it using this icon.
Okay.
And then we can close it.
This intro to Python.
Like I said, you can keep it for notes.
Maybe.
And now let's open a new file.
Okay.
I want to open this file.
I want you to click on Save.
And let's call it Blue Bank, dot pie.
And click save.
Okay.
So you may have noticed that the file type that we are going to be working on for Blue Bank is a JSON
file.
So if you notice the extension in the project brief, which is here, you can see the extension is JSON.
So JSON is a file type that looks similar to dictionaries that we discussed in Project one.
I'll show you how JSON looks.
So I'm just going to open the actual dataset.
Okay.
And you can see that the Jason file has data enclosed in curly brackets.
Right.
And each set of curly brackets have sort of the same keys, but just different values.
Essentially, a Jason files within the curly brackets.
This represents one row of data.
And these are the column names.
So it's just a different format and how we usually set up the data.
But I just wanted to show you how Jason files look.
Now in Python, the good thing is that Python does have a pre-installed package called Jason which can
actually read these types of files.
I'm just going back to Spider.
And what we can do is we can use a library called Jason to help us to read the files.
And while we importing Jason, we can also import pandas to remember for libraries.
One is that you have to install them, and then two, you have to import them if you're going to use
it.
Now what, Jason?
Jason comes prepackaged in Anaconda, so we're fine with that.
We don't need to do a pipe install, Jason.
We just need to imported into our script.
But if you remember, for Pandas, we had to do a puppy install pandas in our command, prompt a terminal
K, which is this year,
and then import it into a python.
But for Jason, we don't need to do that.
So we can just have some libraries.
So let's just say import Jason.
And as always, import pandas as PD.
Usually the way scripts are set out is that your libraries occur first, most in your script, and then
you actual script.
The other thing to note is to note that I didn't bring up in the last project is that you must be very
careful with spacing an indentation on Python.
It means a lot.
So if you are going to space, you know, or tab, make sure that you're doing it for a specific reason
and not just randomly.
All right.
So now that we do that, let's try and read our JSON data.
So there's two ways we can do that.
And I'm just going to come in here and say method one to read JSON data.
Okay.
So are we going to say Jason file as equal to and say open and then open brackets?
Karma and whatever the file name is called.
So I'm just going to go to the file section here where the variable explorer is, and it is this one
here.
Okay.
Some type of such a lone underscore data.
Underscore Jason dot Jason.
Okay.
And then this here just opens a file, and then we need to actually load it.
All right, so then we're going to say data equals Jason load and adjacent file.
Okay, so this opens the Jason file.
So this is our JSON file and it opens it and this actually load data into Python.
Right.
So the function there's a load function in the Jason library where we can open a file.
Okay.
So let's just go back to Variable Explorer.
And also just to note, this is so similar to how we do the pandas functions as well.
If you remember correctly, the last project as well, if you're referring to a function in pandas,
the function name would be here and then pandas would be here and then whatever the function does.
So that formatting stays the same.
Okay.
So in this instance, we're using Jason.
Jason has a load function and we're loading Jason file.
What is Jason File?
Jason file is just opening the specific directory.
Okay, let's just run the script.
You can run the whole script.
Awesome.
Okay.
And now you see we have a list and our data file here.
All right.
And it looks like there is that same data that we saw when we are looking at the JSON data.
Let's double click on it.
Okay.
Definitely not in a data frame or table, which is what we like.
So we definitely need to work on the formatting here.
The other method we can do to load adjacent file, it's very similar to the first one.
Just a different format that you might see.
As we use the word statement.
So if we say something like a wolf and then we say Open.
Loan data.
Jason Dot.
Jason
as.
Jason File.
Data equals Jason.
Dirt load.
Jason.
Well.
And just do a print print data.
Okay.
Now, this is a bit different.
But basically over here we can use something called well and s to declare a variable in another way.
So this here was and as is the same as saying Jason file equals open long data.
Jason.
Right.
But because it's a word statement, there needs to be some sort of formatting specifics.
Okay.
So with this here, you'll notice that we put a colon and then immediately went up into Python indented.
So there's a tab between the beginning of the line until the next.
And.
Python uses indentations to actually separate sort of statements.
If I am describing it properly, so thus here, whatever is indented, whatever is tabbed is all part
of this.
What statement?
Okay.
And then once I move out of the indentation.
So once I go back, it's not part of the statement.
Right.
So ideally, this here means the same as this.
We just writing it differently.
So over here, we're saying with open lone date, adjacent, adjacent as JSON file.
Same thing as saying JSON file equals open load data to date.
Jason.
And then this is exactly the same.
All right.
This data equals JSON load.
Jason file and then I just added a print function, but you actually don't need to have that.
So I'm going to remove that
and let's run this and see if there's any difference.
I'm just selecting from method two down and just run the selection.
Okay.
And exactly the same.
Exactly the same method.
Okay.
I added it in because this is what you might see and sometimes you may want to use this as well.
This is also quite good if you want to do any transformations as well and you keep it all within the
same.
The statement.
And then generally what statements are used to make your code clean and readable.
And then so so it actually executes better if there are any errors as well.
So you'll you will see people using this more than than using this one.
But for now, just it's up to you.
It does the same thing.
Yeah, right.
So I know that this is now stored into a list and it actually does look a bit like a dictionary as well.
And what the lists here they are sort of for different types or ways Python uses to store collections
of data.
There's lists, there's tuples visits and there's dictionaries.
All right.
And like I said before, to create a list, they generally are created out of square brackets, whereas
tuples are on brackets and states are curly brackets.
So I'm just going to go a bit more in detail into lists.
So let's just say we're going to create a list, let's call it lists, and we're going to say it equals
two and let's do Apple.
Banana and pear.
And let's run this.
So let's select that line and run it.
Okay.
So now we have a.
We know this strain, this list, and it's apple.
Banana and pear lists are generally ordered and changeable as well.
And you can also have duplicate values.
So if we have another one called pear.
And I'm just selecting and I'm doing an if nine or just running the selection.
Yeah.
It still allows it.
Everything's good.
There's there's no era right now for lists.
The first item has an index zero.
The second item has an index one.
The third item has an index two and and so on.
So let's just go to a console and let's just say if we had to do something like List zero, which is
going to my console because I do want to continuously run this.
But if we do something else sorry it's not listed the lists zero and press enter.
I can see Apple shows up and let's do lists too.
And you can see here shows up.
Okay.
So we can actually choose specific items in the list using that sort of method of referencing the other
index.
Now remember I told you that lists are ordered and changeable and allow duplicate values, right?
What that means is that if I want to add a new item to this list, it will get added at the back of
the list.
So it's not going to change the order.
Okay, so let's just look at it in a bit more detail and let's do something like it's a pinned to a
list.
Okay.
And we're going to do something like lists dot append.
So append is a function way.
If you want to add, something usually gets added to the end and I do want to add a new fruit.
So let's add cherry.
Okay.
And let's run this.
And now you'll see Cherry is added, but you'll see cherries added at the end.
So if we do a print list here, so let's do a print lists and you can see cherry is added at the end.
Now, what if we actually want to insert maybe another fruit into a specific position?
Okay.
All we can do is, let's say, insert.
Then insert item into a specific position.
Okay.
We're going to do lists dot insert.
And let's just say an index zero.
Let's say an index number one.
I want to insert grape.
Okay.
So I'm going to an index number one.
I'm inserting a grape.
So this is zero.
This is one.
So instead of banana, it's all going to shift down and it's going to be apple grape, banana pear here
or apple grape.
Banana, papaya, cherry.
So let's run this.
And let's have a look at the lists again.
And there you go.
Apple, grape, banana, papaya, cherry.
But also a good thing with lists that are not present in in other collections or data types like us
yet.
It's
also a good thing with lists that maybe are not present in something like a tuple is that you can actually
change items in a list list.
Also a good thing with lists that are actually not present in something like a tuple is that you can
actually change items in a list as well, which is pretty cool.
So you can change change items in a list.
So if we're going to do something like let's well, let's maybe do remove threats to remove so let's
remove items in the list first.
So we're going to say list, let's remove and I want to remove the duplicate pair.
Okay.
So let's run that.
And it's flipping lists in a console.
Now you can see Pier is removed.
Now the other thing we can do is we can also remove the last item.
So if we do lists dot pop.
PUP is a function that removes the last item.
So let's look at that and let's run that.
And I think.
Cherry's going to go.
So let's review lists.
And now you can see Cherry has been removed.
So something like Pop is quite useful.
You know, when you have a list of maybe email addresses or you're a data capture and you know you're
capturing data and you realize you made a mistake in your most recent data entry, you can use Pop.
So that's why I edited it.
And just because some people use Pop four for those specific reasons.
Let's just do background on lists.
I thought it would be nice to add because they are important.
I just couldn't find a way to fit it into our actual data for now.
It is quite important to remember because the lists honestly show up everywhere in Python.
So those are lists.
Now if you click into our data variable and we click into one of these values here,
we get this and we can all see Python is telling us the data type.
Yeah, it's saying that it's a dictionary.
Now, why is it a dictionary?
Well, it has a key and it has a value.
And dictionaries have keys, and they do have values.
Okay.
The other thing to notice about dictionaries is that you can store different types.
So this here policy, it's an integer.
The days with credit line is a float purpose.
Here is a string.
So dictionaries can have different types of data within them.
So how exactly do you create a dictionary and what can you do with a dictionary?
So let's just dive into that for a little bit as well.
So I want you to create a comment area and just say working with dictionaries.
And let's create a dictionary.
So let's call it my dict.
T is equal to and open a curly bracket.
Now just want to just space it out like that.
Give myself more space here.
Right.
And let's say something like name.
Colon.
Dee okay.
And the next one is location.
Colon, South Africa.
And then let's do something like fave color and red.
Just remove the remaining spaces and let's run this.
So just selected and run it.
Okay.
So when you run it, probably say something like invalid syntax.
So because we're missing a comma, so we need commas for dictionaries at the end of each line.
Okay.
Except red.
So in the last line, you don't need a comma.
And that's running again.
Okay.
There you go.
My addict has not shown up.
And you can see immediately it's a dictionary and it's telling us it has sort of three roles or three
keys.
Name, location and favorite color.
Now you can also store, like I said, a different data type.
So these are all strings or they all objects.
So if I just say a comma here and let's do something like lucky number.
Let's put seven and let's run this again.
So we had to put a comma here and we had to put a comma here.
We don't need to put it in the last line.
Okay, let's let and run that.
And you can see it works just as fine.
Even the lucky numbers seven and the rest are strings.
Now if we double click this can see the format here is that it has a key, it has a type a size and
a corresponding value.
Let's look at some other features of dictionaries so you can access other keys as well.
So
let's just say I just wanted to access maybe the color.
So I'm going to say color is equal to my dict.
And just like how it is in data frames, when you want to access a specific column, it's exactly the
same.
And it's just a print color.
And let's just run the these two lines.
Okay.
And you can see that color.
We now just extracted a specific key, which is color.
And it gave me what we wanted.
And then if ever we needed maybe a list of keys showing up, we can do that as well.
So let's say to get a list of keys, you can do something like my dict dot keys.
So let's just look at that and run it again.
And these are all the keys that are in my dict.
Similarly, if you want to get a list of values
to get a list of
values.
Okay.
Do my dict dot.
And this values.
Let's run that.
So select that and run the selection.
Okay.
And these are all the values.
You can also get a list of items to get.
To get a list of items can save my ticket.
Dot items.
And let's run that.
Okay.
And these are just the individual items.
So name like each roll almost named location.
South Africa.
Favorite color red.
Lucky number seven.
And then the last thing we can also do that's quite cool is we can add a new variable.
So to add when you key a new key variable, we can say very similar again to data frames.
My indicate gender is equal is equal to female.
Well, I can't spell today.
All right.
And it's just say print my dict can.
Let's just run the two lines.
Rookie error here needs to be in quotation marks.
And it's just run the two lines and now you can see gender appears and female and if we click the name
in the variable explorer can see gender appears and female.
Okay.
So you went a bit on a tangent, but I did want to note that because like I said, listen, dictionaries
are quite important and it's really good for you to understand those key concepts.
So back to the actual project.
Now we have our data in data in the file name or the variable name data.
It's a list.
It doesn't look great.
As you can see, we want it in a table form.
We want it in a data frame.
That's always the the good goal.
So we're going to work on that.
So before I do that, I just want to copy the our dictionary and list notes and I'm going to cut it
so you can command or control X or I click and say Cut, and I'm just going to post a pasted in my intro
to Python notebook.
So here, I'm just going to paste it here.
And I'm just going to come on to control S and save it.
Okay.
Just going to comment on just after the spot here.
I'm just going to say working with the lists.
Right.
All right.
And then save that.
And then just you can go back to blue bank pie, blue banker pie, and then you can save this as.
All right.
Okay.
So as I was saying, how would I transform this data file, which is a list?
And it's really an ugly format to work on to a nice data frame.
Okay.
So let's say transform to data frame,
let's say enter and let's call it loan data is equal to PDD.
Sounds familiar.
We know what PD is.
PD is pandas.
Pandas has this really neat function called data frame, and it will transform your list to a data frame.
Okay, so what are we going to transform in this bracket?
Our list file, which is called data.
Okay.
Let's look at that and let's run that selection.
Awesome.
And now good news.
We can see loan data is quite nice.
It's in a data frame.
It has some rows, it has some columns.
And also we can see the column names.
So let's just double click on loan data.
And we can see all the columns are there and everything is looking good.
So before in this lecture, I just want to quickly let's just go over the columns.
And I think also the columns are in the slide pack because they are quite there's a lot of abbreviations
in there.
So I'm just going to go through the columns.
Okay.
All right.
Let's go through this.
Okay.
So let's do it.
So we have created policy.
And from what I can tell, it's either a one or zero.
And one is if the customer meets the credit underwriting criteria of blue bank and zero is if they don't.
So I think most people would be one because why would they be given a loan if they don't meet the actual
criteria for that loan?
There may be a few exceptions, but I think majority of these borrowers do meet that credit policy.
And I think each row of the data represents one borrower.
If that that helps.
Yeah.
The next one is purpose and the purpose of the borrower, why the borrower took or has taken the loan.
All right.
So debt consolidation, it's a credit card loan, home improvement.
So, you know, car loans, etc., would come through.
And in this small business, in this column.
So reasons to why the person took out their own interest rate.
So this is the interest rate of the loan as a proportion.
So a rate of 11% would be stored as 0.11.
And borrowers judged by Blue Bank to be more risky are assigned higher interest rates.
So obviously here, if a borrower is more risky, so maybe they don't have enough income to pay back
the loans or they haven't been paying back the loans, etc. Your interest rate will be higher than someone
who's very low risk.
They all have low interest rates.
Installment.
So this is the monthly installment owed by the borrower if the loan is funded.
So how much they pay each month?
Probably a minimum.
And these are in dollars, by the way, the long annual income.
So that is the natural log of the borrower's income for annual income.
So to get the actual annual income, we'll need to do the inverse.
So we'll need to get the exponent of this number will give us the actual annual income.
DTI is the debt to income ratio of the borrower.
So the amount of debt divided by the annual income.
Okay.
So obviously, if your DTI is greater than one, then your borrower has more debt than income, but
less than one.
Then you borrower has more income than debt.
All right.
It's I mean, this isn't really very accurate in general just because I mean, people's house loans
and stuff and mortgages all definitely make you get a higher DTI than your annual income because your
mortgage can be worth hundreds and thousands of dollars, but you're on your income much less than that.
So I'm just saying that this isn't the end all and be all.
Someone has a high DTI that could just be a normal, non risky borrower, but just have something like
a house loan
cycle that your FICO credit score.
So if you are in the U.S., you obviously know what it means if you're not in the US.
I think the US bases people's risk on credit score and if you applying for something like a house loan
or a car loan, etc., a good credit score will enable you to get the loan and a bad one is basically
you get blacklisted.
So for credit scores, I think it is anything.
So from 300 to 400 is very poor.
400 to 600 is poor.
600 to 660 is fair.
662 780 is good.
And 782 850 is excellent.
So basically anyone below 600 would be a poor credit, would have a poor credit score.
So these are in new lecture slides in case you want to refer back to them.
And then days with credit line is the number of days the borrower has had a credit line.
Okay.
So these look like quite decent sized loans.
So the credit line would be high.
I mean, these aren't short term like 30 day loans, revolving balance, borrowers revolving balance
or the amount unpaid at the end of the credit card billing cycle.
Okay.
So how much basically how much do they have left over again in revolving utility or utilization rate?
Is the borrower's revolving line utilization rate the amount of credit the line?
So the amount of credit line used relative to the total credit available.
So what this means is that so this person here has used only 25% of their total credit available, which
is good.
Inquiries within the last six months.
This is if any sort of credit institutions have inquired the borrower about something like there's a
lot of inquiries.
There's an issue because of borrowers not paying or something's wrong.
So you don't want this to be populated that the number this is delinquency is a delinquency or de-link.
Two years.
I actually can't see in my notes the actual what's the full field name for this?
But this is the number of times a borrower had been 30 days past due on a payment in the past two years.
So if this is a high number, it means that the borough obviously is always late for his payment.
Okay.
Public records, the borrowers, number of derogatory public records.
So if they file for bankruptcy, texts, issues, judgments, etc., also, Don, this populated and
then with other loan has been partly fully paid or not as not fully paid.
Okay.
So quite a lot of data in this.
But you know, there's a lot we can tell whether borrower is a risky borrower or not.
I mean, just based, just based.
And the last few columns, we can actually give them quite good answers.
And then as you can see, we probably need to do a lot of transformation in cleaning here.
So, for example, these FICO scores, it would be good to actually have a column with the correct category
that the borrower is in.
So 680 is actually a good five COSCO.
So it would be nice to have a column like that.
It would be nice to get the actual annual income.
So we just need an exponent of this as well and and some other things that we can do.
Perfect.
Okay.
So using this and maybe if you want to go back to the slide deck and have a look at the fields again
you are most welcome to.
So they are present in the in the slide and the slides for the lecture.
But I think we are done here.
We know a bit more about the data.
We've loaded it in.
It's a nice data frame.
So in the next lecture, what we can do is you can get started on the data tuning and transformation.
So I'll see you then by.